<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Resumos xmlns:xsd="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA001</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Chronic systemic pain genes may have a role in the development of Apical Periodontitis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Francio JQA*, Neves GST, Letra A, Carneiro E</Autores>
		<Universidade>Endodontia - PONTIFÍCIA UNIVERSIDADE CATÓLICA DO PARANÁ.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Chronic pain (CP) has affected 30% of people worldwide. Apical periodontitis (AP) is a chronic inflammatory disease characterized by inflammation and destruction of periradicular tissues that result from an infected root canal system. Pain is often seen as a clinical manifestation of AP for which the pathogenesis and molecular players overlap with other CP conditions. For the selection of candidate genes, PubMed was searched using specific terms. 173 genes from studies investigating different chronic conditions were selected. Publications were screened by title and abstract; in cases where this presented insufficient information, the text of the publication was read. 16 genes were finally selected (&lt;em&gt;BDNF&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CAMK4&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;COMT&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CTSG&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CRHBP&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;HTR2A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;IFRD1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;IL1A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;KCNS1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;MMP9&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;RAMP1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;SCN9A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;SCN11A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TIMP1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TFNA&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TRPV1&lt;/em&gt;). AP tissue samples (n=42) were collected immediately upon apical endodontic surgery. RNA extraction was performed using Trizol and cDNA was synthesized. Control tissues comprised healthy periodontal ligament tissue samples. mRNA levels of target genes were evaluated using SYBR green chemistry in using RT-qPCR and normalized to &lt;em&gt;GAPDH&lt;/em&gt;. Data analysis was performed using the 2&lt;sup&gt;&amp;#8722;&amp;#916;&amp;#916;Ct&lt;/sup&gt; method. P-values &amp;#8804; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>&lt;em&gt;CAMK4&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;COMT&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;MMP9&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TIMP1 &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;TNFA &lt;/em&gt;were significantly up-regulated in AP tissues. Our findings suggest that these genes may have an important role in the chronic pain associated with Apical Periodontitis. Identifying genes expressed in AP improves knowledge of the condition and provide insight into new therapies.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio></Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA002</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Development and validation of a self-report instrument for the screening of apical periodontitis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Franciscatto GJ*, Réquia EC, Rossi-Fedele G, Gauer G, Gomes MS</Autores>
		<Universidade>PONTIFÍCIA UNIVERSIDADE CATÓLICA DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study aimed to develop and validate a self-report instrument to identify patients with apical periodontitis (SRAP). The content and face validities of a 45-item self-report questionnaire were evaluated and the construct validity was tested in a population of 179 individuals through Factor Analysis for Mixed Data (FAMD) and reliability tests (analysis of internal consistency and test-retest). For accuracy evaluation, the SRAP was completely answered by 182 individuals. Diagnostic findings of apical periodontitis (AP) were obtained from panoramic radiographs analysis. The area under the receiver operator curve (AUROC), accuracy, sensitivity (SS), specificity (SP), positive (PPV) and negative predictive values (NPV), positive (PLR) and negative likelihood ratios (NLR) were calculated. After face and content validation, 38 items remained in the pool. After FAMD, 8 items were retained with a Cronbach's alpha of 0.85. The model included 3 factors that explained 33.05% of variance in data: history of endodontic treatment, oral health self-evaluation and history of oral trauma. The prevalence of AP was 54.3%. The SRAP values for the diagnosis of AP were: AUROC (0.685), accuracy (0.615); SS (0.636); SP (0.590); PPV (0.649); NPV (0.576); PLR (1.207) and NLR (0.615).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The 8-item SRAP presented good indexes of construct validity and reliability, showing a predictive power for AP in up to 65% of cases. The SRAP is a low cost, fast and easy to apply instrument, representing an encouraging tool to be used in large-scale population screenings and public health scenarios.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001 | Australian Academy of Sciences N° 2018)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA003</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Effects of nano-sized sodium hexametaphosphate and fluoride on dual-species biofilms of &lt;em&gt;Streptococcus mutans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/em&gt;</Titulo>
		<Autores>Sampaio C*, Delbem ACB, Fernandes AVP, Hosida TY, Morais LA, Camargo ER, Monteiro DR, Pessan JP</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Preventiva e Restauradora - UNIVERSIDADE ESTADUAL PAULISTA - ARAÇATUBA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study evaluated the effects of nano-sized sodium hexametaphosphate (HMPnano), combined or not with fluoride (F), on dual-species biofilms of &lt;em&gt;Streptococcus mutans &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Candida albicans&lt;/em&gt;. Solutions containing micrometric HMP (HMPmicro) or HMPnano were prepared at 0.5 or 1%, combined or not with 1,100 ppm F; 1,100 ppm F and artificial saliva were tested as positive and negative controls, respectively. Dual-species biofilms of &lt;em&gt;S. mutans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;C. albicans&lt;/em&gt;, grown in microtiter plates, were treated (1 min) with the solutions at 72, 78 and 96 h from the beginning of their formation. Biofilms were analyzed by colony-forming unit counting (CFU), metabolic activity (XTT assay), and production of total biomass (crystal violet assay). Data were submitted to ANOVA or Kruskal Wallis test, followed by Tukey's or Student-Newman-Keuls' tests (p&lt;0.05). HMPnano at 1% + F led to the highest CFU reduction of &lt;em&gt;S. mutans&lt;/em&gt;, followed by HMP micro at 1% + F and positive control (similar to each other), and the remaining groups; CFU counts of &lt;em&gt;C. albicans&lt;/em&gt; were not affected by any solution assessed. Furthermore, HMPnano at 1% led to significant lower metabolic activity compared to all other groups (except for HMPnano at 1% + F). Also, all test solutions promoted significant reductions in biofilm biomass compared to both positive and negative controls.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>It can be concluded that HMPnano promoted higher antibiofilm effects compared with its micrometric counterpart for most of the variables assessed, besides having a synergist action with F on CFU reduction of &lt;em&gt;S. mutans&lt;/em&gt;.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001 | CAPES N° 88881.068437/2014-01 | CNPq N° 123611/2019-9)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA004</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Adrenergic signaling and periodontitis: insights on innate immunity response and &lt;em&gt;P. gingivalis&lt;/em&gt; virulence factors in an invertebrate model</Titulo>
		<Autores>Moraes RM*, Stossi F, Garcia MT, Barros PP, Ribeiro JL, Anbinder AL</Autores>
		<Universidade>Biociências e Diagnóstico Bucal - INSTITUTO DE CIÊNCIA E TECNOLOGIA / ICT-UNESP-SJC.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Stress is a risk factor for periodontitis, however, the interrelationship between stress (adrenergic system), innate immune response and virulence of periodontopathogens (e.g., &lt;em&gt;Porphyromonas gingivalis-Pg&lt;/em&gt;) is still unclear. The study of stress in humans involves variables that are difficult to control, besides individual variations, the complexity of immune response and microbiota. Invertebrate models are a good alternative, as they have similar innate immune response and enable controlled infections. We investigated the action of adrenergic signaling by comparing norepinephrine-NE (&amp;#945; and &amp;#946; agonist) and isoproterenol-ISO (&amp;#946; agonist) on &lt;em&gt;Galleria mellonella&lt;/em&gt; immune response and &lt;em&gt;Pg&lt;/em&gt; virulence. Dose and time-responses on toxicity and hemocyte density were measured. Both ligands showed opposite effects 30 minutes post-injection: ISO increased the hemocyte number by stimulating sessile hemocyte detachment from the fat body, and NE decreased it. This phenotype correlated with a protective effect of ISO on larval mortality after &lt;em&gt;Pg&lt;/em&gt; injection, while NE enhanced the death rate. ISO and NE had similar effects on melanization. &lt;em&gt;Pg&lt;/em&gt; was also cultivated in the presence of ISO or NE and then injected into the larvae, to evaluate the direct effects of the ligands on bacterial virulence. ISO-grown bacteria increased the death rate compared to standard &lt;em&gt;Pg&lt;/em&gt; controls, and NE had no significant effect.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>There is a complex interrelation among stress receptors, innate immune response and bacterial virulence, and their balance is what determines the infection's ultimate outcome.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 2018/25933-3 | FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/26461-5 | FAPs - FAPESP N° 2018/21701-0)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA005</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Metabolomic identification of novel salivary biomarkers for diagnostic and monitoring Diabetes</Titulo>
		<Autores>Moura DV*, Caixeta DC, Santos P, Martins MM, Goulart LR, Sabino-Silva R</Autores>
		<Universidade>Fisiologia - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE UBERLÂNDIA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The diagnostic and monitoring of glycemia is an invasive and painful in diabetes mellitus (DM).Consequently, the search for non-invasive diagnostic biomarkers is of great interest in DM. The limitation to use saliva in clinical settings can be related to the reduced chemical composition knowledge. Here, a characterization of the salivary metabolome is presented in a diabetic animal model. Fluid chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry with time-of-flight system were employed to spot the metabolites in rats saliva. Fifteen Wistar rats were divided in non-diabetic (ND), diabetic (D) and diabetic 6U-treated of insulin (D6U). DM was induced by an intraperitoneal injection (60 mg/kg) of streptozotocin (STZ). The animals were submitted to 28 days of diabetes, and on the 21st day, the insulin- or placebo-treatment was started (#CEUA 13/16). The glycemia and urinary glucose confirmed the diabetic state. The metabolic salivary profile identified hundreds of novel compounds with potential to discriminate diabetes. Principal Component Analysis and clustering indicates 3 main candidates as novel salivary metabolites for salivary screening of diabetes: N-Arachidonoyl tyrosine, 1-11-Eicosenoyl-Triacylglycerol and Dimethylphosphatidylethanolamine (22:5(7Z/24:1(15Z) HMDB, (ANOVA).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Altogether, this salivary metabolomic analysis indicates novel salivary metabolites candidates to be applied in salivary diagnostic salivary platforms for non-invasive diabetic diagnostic platforms and for the salivary monitoring tool during insulin treatment.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° (#23038.014934/2020-59). | FAPEMIG N° (#APQ-02872-16) | INCT-TeraNano N° (465669/2014-0))&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA006</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Selective Outcome Reporting (SOR) in Pediatric Dentistry restorative treatment Randomized Clinical Trials - A systematic Review</Titulo>
		<Autores>Elagami RA*, Tedesco TK, Pannuti CM, Seabra G, Braga MM, Mendes FM, Raggio DP</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontopediatria e Ortodontia - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>We aimed to evaluate the prevalence of SOR in the randomized clinical trials focusing on restorative treatment in primary molars. We searched for RCTs protocol registries in the ClinicalTrials.gov and WHO platform up to April/2021. We included any study classified as an RCT, with two or more experimental arms that evaluated any restorative treatment on primary teeth. The registries that did not result in any publications were excluded. Our search strategy identified 294 registries and 31 publications were included for data extraction. We have also calculated the median of journals' impact factors. Chi-square test was performed with 5% significance level. Our results found that the prevalence of SOR was identified in 19 papers (61.3%). The most common reason was a discrepancy in the primary outcome timeframe (48.4%). Twenty-six (83.9%) of the trials were registered retrospectively. Also, a discrepancy in sponsorship was identified in 22 (71%) of the trials. SOR was associated with the discrepancy in the follow-up period (p=0.003), with no association with registration timing (p=0.948). The impact factor of the journals ranged from 0.213 - 5.79. We found SOR in 9 (29%) of the six high impact factor journals and 10 (32.3%) of the eight with low impact.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Consequently, we emphasized the importance of transparency in RCT focusing on restorative care in children, including properly prospective registration and declaration of any discrepancy in the final manuscript, helping to avoid spin in science.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA007</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Probiotic: &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; evaluation of the effect on progression of periapical lesions, through microscopic analysis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Araujo LDC*, Segato RAB, Messora MR, Furlaneto FAC, Salvador SLS, Nelson-Filho P, Pucinelli CM, Silva LAB</Autores>
		<Universidade>UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of the present study was to evaluate the effect of the probiotic &lt;em&gt;Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis&lt;/em&gt; (B. lacti) HN019 &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;, as an irrigation solution for root canals in rats' teeth with induced periapical lesion. The animals were divided in four groups, as follows: group I: healthy teeth; group II: periapical lesion; group III: 2.5% sodium hypochlorite; group IV: probiotic, in 7, 21, 42 days. The probiotic irrigating solution was formulated by adding the probiotic at 2.7x 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; CFU in water medium and 2.0% of carboxymethylcellulose. The root canals were irrigated on day 0 and days 3, 7, 14, 21, 28 and 35 days, after periapical lesion induction. The mandible samples were stained in HE and analyzed under optical microscopy to describe the characteristics of the pulp tissue and the apical and periapical regions, in parallel with the morphometric analysis of the extension of the lesion area, osteoclast marking (TRAP), immunohistochemistry to identify markers of the osteoclastogenesis (RANK, RANK-L and OPG) and microbiological analysis using the Brown &amp; Brenn technique. The data were analyzed using software R, version 4.0.0, applying SAS 9.4 and Graph Pad Prism 5, with a significance level of 5%. The histopathological, immunohistochemical and microbiological analysis parameters in probiotic groups were significantly better when compared to groups without periapical lesion and 2.5% sodium hypochlorite (p&lt;0.05).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Therefore, probiotic demonstrated a therapeutic potential on the progression of periapical injuries.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPESP N° 2018/22038-3)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA008</Sigla>
		<Titulo>A microtomographic and histological analysis of the induced orthodontic movement in obese rats</Titulo>
		<Autores>Horta KC*, Paula-Silva FWG, Stuani MBS, Elias LLK, Flores Mir C, Graf D, Consolaro A, Matsumoto MAN</Autores>
		<Universidade>UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>To evaluate the effect of obesity over induced tooth movement (ITM) through computerized micro-tomography and histological analyzes in obesity-induced Wistar rats. Forty rats of approximately 125 g were randomly assigned into four groups according to obesity status and ITM duration (mesial movement of the left maxillary first molar for seven and fourteen days). Eighty hemi-maxillas were processed for histological and micro-CT examination. ITM was measured in the micro-CTs. The number of osteoclasts was analyzed through staining of enzyme tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase. Also, the presence or absence of focal hyalinization (FH), frontal bone resorption (FBR), and active root resorption (ARRC) were evaluated in sections stained with Hematoxylin-Eosin. Data were submitted to appropriate statistical analysis using Graph Pad Prism 5.0 and Stata13 (&amp;#945;=0.05) Obese animals showed higher rates of ITM after seven (p=0.037) and fourteen days (p&amp;#8804;0.001) than non-obese animals. A higher quantity of osteoclast was observed after seven days of ITM in obese animals (p=0.043). Low frequencies of FH were observed after seven days of ITM. After seven days of ITM high frequency of FBR and low frequency of ARRC were found in obese animals, while, medium frequencies of FBR and ARRC were seen in non-obese animals. Low and medium frequencies of FBR were observed in non-obese and obese animals respectively after fourteen days of ITM.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Obese rats showed significantly higher rates of molar movement and different morphological responses in the surrounding bone and periodontium to ITM.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES | FAPESP)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA009</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Self-assembling peptide-containing electrospun scaffolds for mineralized tissue regeneration</Titulo>
		<Autores>Araújo IJS*, Ferreira JA, Daghrery A, Ribeiro JS, Puppin-Rontani RM, Bottino MC</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Restauradora - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Combining scaffolds and bioactive molecules to mimic the extracellular matrix (ECM) is vital for mineralized tissue regeneration strategies. Electrospinning allows the fabrication of ECM-like scaffolds. Meanwhile, self-assembling peptide (SAP) P&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;-4 is applied to repair early caries lesions. Thus, to explore SAP effectivity on mineralized tissue regeneration, distinct concentrations of P&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;-4 were adsorbed in electrospun scaffolds. After scaffolds immersion in simulated body fluid, mineral precipitation was verified by Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM). FTIR and XRD detected functional groups and crystalline phases, respectively. Cytocompatibility, mineralization, and gene expression assays were conducted using stem cells from human exfoliated deciduous teeth. &lt;em&gt;In vivo&lt;/em&gt; bone regeneration was assessed by defects in rat calvaria. ANOVA and Tukey posthoc tests verified differences for cytocompatibility, mineralization, gene expression, and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; regeneration (&amp;#945;=0.05). SEM images indicated mineral precipitation. FTIR and XRD confirmed apatite-like formation and crystallization induced by SAP-containing scaffolds. SAP-containing scaffolds were cytocompatible, stimulated cells to mineralization, and upregulated bone-related genes' expression. Also, substantial &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; bone regeneration was induced after eight weeks. Histological analyses evidenced homogeneous bone formation.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Finally, SAP-containing scaffolds are promising bioinspired constructs for mineralized tissue regeneration in the oral and craniofacial complex.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 88887.368381/2019-00 | NIH N° R01DE026578)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA010</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Dental trauma splints for mixed dentition - A finite element analysis of splint material, extension, missing teeth, and PDL representation</Titulo>
		<Autores>Vilela ABF*, Soares PBF, Versluis A, Soares CJ</Autores>
		<Universidade>Dentística - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE UBERLÂNDIA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study evaluated the effect on the mobility of splint materials and extensions for avulsed central incisor, stabilized with and without the adjacent incisor under horizontal and vertical loading with different periodontal ligament (PDL) conditions. Seventeen 3D models were created from a CBCT of a 7-year-old patient without erupted permanent upper lateral incisors. A new method was created to simulate the avulsion injury, 1000N palatal load was applied on the central incisor creating increased alveolus with 0.45mm of PDL thickness. Wire-composite splints with 0.9mm (WCS) or 1.0mm nylon-composite splints (NCS) were created with and without the adjacent upper central incisor and four splint extensions were simulated. PDL conditions were investigated, simulating liquefied PDL or PDL with silicon. Mobility was calculated under horizontal, intrusive and extrusive loading. The NCS allowed higher mobility than the WCS, irrespective of extension, PDL or load conditions. During horizontal loading, silicon-like PDL allowed around 0.2mm mobility of the avulsed tooth with the WCS, similar to the intact tooth, whereas liquefied PDL allowed 25% higher mobility with a WCS than NCS.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>A 1.0mm NCS seems to be a good option for splinting avulsion injuries during mixed dentition. The NCS provided flexibility for PDL healing while maintaining stability, even when missing adjacent teeth. Extensions beyond directly adjacent teeth did not alter mobility with the NCS, but should still be considered extra protection in case of bond failure or exfoliation.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001 | FINEP N° FAPEMIG | CNPq)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA011</Sigla>
		<Titulo>A novel graphene-catechol dental sealant: properties and perspectives</Titulo>
		<Autores>Pereira R*, Rischka K, Lins RBE, Stamboroski S, Mainardi MCAJ, Aguiar FHB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Restauradora - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study aimed to assess the particles dispersion (D), antibacterial action (A), bond strength (BS), fracture pattern (FP), Vickers nanohardness (N), indentation modulus (IM), indentation creep (IC) and elastic part of indentation work (E) of dental sealants. An experimental sealant was incorporated by graphene (G) and graphene modified by L-dopa (Gd) in 0 and 0.25 concentrations (wt%). The D was assessed visually and microscopically. For A test, samples (n=10) were incubated with &lt;em&gt;S.mutans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;L.casei&lt;/em&gt;. Aliquots were spread on agar-plates. Colonies Forming Units (CFU) were quantified. For BS test, enamel surfaces of bovine teeth (n=8) were restored with sealant pillars, according to the groups. Pillars were submitted to microshear test. FP was quantified. For mechanical tests, samples (n=8) were assessed in a mechanical analyzer initially (T&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;) and after 10 days of water storage (T&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;). Data were statistically analyzed using One-way or Two-way ANOVA and Bonferroni tests. Gd was better dispersed than G. Control presented the highest number of &lt;em&gt;S.mutans&lt;/em&gt; CFU. &lt;em&gt;L.casei&lt;/em&gt; growth decreased as follows: Control &gt; G &gt; Gd. The BS was similar among groups. All groups showed mainly enamel-sealant adhesive FP. In general, at T&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; and T&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, Gd presented the highest N and IM, while Control obtained the highest IC, and both G and Gd had the highest E. From T&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; to T&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; only Control had its NH decreased. Other properties were not affected.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Gd sealant is a promising material, as it presents antibacterial activity, adequate bond strength, high mechanical strength, and still elasticity to absorb tensions.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 88887.368696/2019-00 | Fraunhofer-Gesellschaft zur Förderung der angewandten Forschung e. V.)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA012</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Mechanical behavior of different core and veneer designs for all-ceramic crowns: 3D Finite element analysis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Carvalho ABG*, Andrade GS, Tribst JPM, Ramos NC, Luz JN, Borges ALS, Saavedra GSFA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Restauradora - INSTITUTO DE CIÊNCIA E TECNOLOGIA / ICT-UNESP-SJC.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>To evaluate the mechanical behavior of different core and veneer designs for all-ceramic crowns. Using the finite element analysis (FEA) three designs were considered: CC - Conventional bilayer crown; MCV - Modified cutback core with ceramic veneer; MCCV - Modified cutback core with cemented machined ceramic veneer. Using a modeling software (Rhinoceros 6.0SR8), a superior central incisor model was created with a full-crown preparation and replicated to receive the three crown designs. Lithium disilicate (E=102.8 GPa) was the core material for all situations, fluorapatite (E=68 GPa) (CC/MCV) and leucite (E=65.8 GPa) (MCCV) ceramics were simulated as veneer materials. Models were exported to a FEA software to evaluate the stress distribution on crowns. All interfaces were considered bonded and materials considered isotropic, homogeneous, and linearly elastic. A 400 N load was applied at 45°, at 1 mm distant from the incisal edge and Maximum Principal Stress (MPa) criteria was used to evaluate the results. MCCV presented a more uniform stress distribution, while CC and MCV presented higher stress concentration in critical areas. The highest stress peak was on core of CC model (70.1 MPa). For veneer layer, the peaks were around 19 MPa. MCV core presented tensile stress peaks of 65.9, and veneer of 17.9 MPa. For MCCV, the peak in the core was 68.4 MPa with lower values in veneer layer (15.1 MPa).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The new all-ceramic crown design with a cemented veneer in modified core seems to be a promising alternative, improving the mechanical behavior and reducing stress on central incisors.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPESP N° 2020/07693-5)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA013</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Salivary proteomic predictors of radiotherapy-induced toxicities in oral cancer patients</Titulo>
		<Autores>Palmier NR*, Ribeiro ACP, Brandão TB, Rossi T, Lopes MA, Migliorati CA, Paes Leme AF, Silva ARS</Autores>
		<Universidade>Diagnóstico Oral - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Great medical advances have been achieved through personalized, molecular-based diagnosis and treatment. Therefore, this study tested the hypothesis that targeted proteins are associated with oral toxicities severity in oral and oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) patients undergoing radiotherapy (RT). Liquid biopsy was performed by subjecting whole saliva of 35 advanced OSCC patients to targeted proteomic analysis through selected reaction monitoring-mass spectrometry (SRM-MS) including 56 targeted proteins, and their abundance was correlated with clinical outcomes (Mann-Whitney and ANOVA with post-hoc Tukey HSD tests). Xerostomia, dysphagia, odynophagia, dysgeusia and oral candidiasis (OC) were daily evaluated using the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events grading system (NCI CTCAE, Version 4.0, 2010) and the visual analogue scale. Overall, 90% of patients developed RT-induced oral toxicities and SRM-MS results indicated that 27 proteins, mainly related to biological processes such as innate immune responses, inflammatory response, cell migration, peptidase inhibitor activity, and iron coordination, were correlated with more severe grades (p&lt;0.05) of dysgeusia, dysphagia, xerostomia, odynophagia, and OC in 68%, 60%, 43%, 34%, and 26% of patients, respectively.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>This study originally demonstrates salivary proteomic predictors of debilitating RT-induced acute oral toxicities in late-stage OSCC patients, improving clinical protocols for personalized supportive care in Oncology.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 2018/04657-8)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA014</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Photobiomodulation therapy in Burning Mouth Syndrome: a randomized double-blind controlled trial</Titulo>
		<Autores>Marotta BM*, Freitas GDH, Hanna R, Gallo CB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Diagnóstico Oral - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Burning Mouth Syndrome (BMS) is characterized by a burning sensation despite the absence of clinical signs and topical clonazepam is considered the gold-standard therapy. This randomized double-blind controlled trial compared the effect of photobiomodulation therapy (PBM) and topical clonazepam for symptom relief in BMS patients. Fifteen patients were eligible and randomly allocated in the intervention or control group. The intervention group underwent 6 sessions of PBM with infrared low power laser (880nm, 90mW, 6J/cm2), which was simulated in the control group turning down the device and reproducing its signaling sounds. The control group rinsed 5 ml of 0.5mg/ml clonazepam solution 3 times a day for 21 days, simulated in the intervention group by rinsing a solution without clonazepam, to ensure the blindness of the received intervention. All patients were evaluated according the IMMPACT-II recommendations for outcome assessment in pain clinical trials, by a blinded research, at the baseline, end of treatment, 30 and 60 days of follow-up. Both treatments offered a significant symptom relief in BMS patients, according the numerical rating scale, without a significant difference between them. PBM provided an earlier effect, maintained for at least 30 days. And topical clonazepam had a slightly higher long-term effect at the 60 day follow-up at other outcomes measures, such as brief pain inventory and oral related quality of life.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>PBM and topical clonazepam are effective in controlling pain symptom in BMS patients.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA015</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Using point coordinates to measure root canal curvature in periapical radiograph and CBCT images using free software</Titulo>
		<Autores>Gialain IO*, Yanaguizawa WH, Fontana CE, Caldeira CL, Cavalcanti MGP</Autores>
		<Universidade>Ciências Odontológicas Integradas - UNIVERSIDADE DE CUIABÁ.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study proposed to demonstrate a technique to calculate root canal curvature on 2D and 3D images using point coordinate, named Point Method (PM), and further compare these methods to the most used method (Schneider). The total sample comprised 120 teeth (30 upper lateral incisors, 30 lower premolars, 30 upper molars, and 30 lower molars), with no radiopaque material on the root canal or pulp chamber. Each tooth underwent periapical radiograph and CBCT exams, and the curvature was analyzed by three different methods - Schneider, 2D PM, and 3D PM. Schneider and 2D PM were performed on periapical radiograph and 3D PM on CBCT. Point Method analysis was made placing points on the canal lumen with a vertical distance of 1mm among points. Using open-source software, the coordinates for each point were transferred into a spreadsheet with analytical geometry formulas. A repeated measures test was made to compare angular values among the methods and an independent measures test was performed to compare the dental groups and the root thirds. The mean curvature angle values found using 3D PM (89.01°) were significantly higher when compared to 2D PM (56.72°) and Schneider (34.62°) for all dental groups. Multirooted teeth had a greater mean curvature angle than single-rooted and the apical third also presented the most curved root canals amongst the root thirds.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The results presented herein show that 3D curvature was higher when compared with 2D analysis. Higher curvature angle values were found at the apical third and on multirooted teeth.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 1570958)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA016</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Periodontal Collapse and Incipient Vascular Abnormalities forming a cluster at the end of 2nd decade of life: a population-based study</Titulo>
		<Autores>Costa CM*, Costa SA, Souza SFC, Alves CMC, Thomaz EBAF, Silva AAM, Ribeiro CCC</Autores>
		<Universidade>Programa de Pós-graduação Em Odontologia - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO MARANHÃO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Periodontitis and cardiovascular disease continuums are associated with each other in late adulthood; we hypothesize this cluster may start as early as adolescence. Thus, we explored the association between initial periodontal collapse and incipient vascular abnormalities at the end of 2nd decade of life. Population-based sample from RPS Birth Cohort Consortium, follow-up at 18-19 years, São Luís (n=2515). The theoretical model explored the complex structure between &lt;em&gt;Initial Periodontitis&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Cardiovascular Risk&lt;/em&gt;, adjusted to socioeconomic status, smoking, alcohol, and obesity, through Structural Equation Modelling. The &lt;em&gt;Cardiovascular Risk&lt;/em&gt; was a latent variable representing the shared variance of carotid-femoral pulse wave velocity, systolic and diastolic blood pressures. &lt;em&gt;Initial Periodontitis&lt;/em&gt; representing the shared variance of visible plaque index, bleeding on probing, probing depth &amp;#8805;4mm, and clinical attachment loss &amp;#8805;3mm. Socioeconomic Status reduced the &lt;em&gt;Initial Periodontitis&lt;/em&gt; (Standardized Coefficient -SC: -0.132; p&lt;0.001) and the &lt;em&gt;Cardiovascular Risk&lt;/em&gt; values (SC: 0.069; p= 0.032); Obesity increased &lt;em&gt;Initial Periodontitis&lt;/em&gt; (SC: 0.111; p=0.001) and &lt;em&gt;Cardiovascular Risk&lt;/em&gt; values (SC: 0.390; p=&lt;0.001). The &lt;em&gt;Cardiovascular Risk&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Initial Periodontitis&lt;/em&gt; associations were bidirectional ones (SC= 0.079; p=0.032).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The initial periodontal collapse and incipient vascular abnormalities in young formed a cluster. The attempt to reduce the diseases continuums should begin much early and direct to their common risk factors.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CNPq)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA017</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Protease-activated receptor 1 (PAR&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;) enhances ectopic bone formation in human periodontal ligament stem cell (hPDLSC) sheets &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;</Titulo>
		<Autores>Alves T*, Gasparoni LM, Balzarini D, Albuquerque-Souza E, Rovai ES, Mendoza AAH, Sipert CR, Holzhausen M</Autores>
		<Universidade>UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>We evaluated the osteogenic outcomes underlying PAR&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; activation and how it affects bone formation in hPDLSC sheets in vivo. Briefly, hPDLSCs were obtained from 3 patients. Groups were: control, osteogenic and osteogenic + PAR&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; activation by TFLLR-NH2 for 2, 7 and 14 days. PAR&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; osteogenic potential pathways Wnt/&amp;#946;-catenin, TGF-&amp;#946;RI, MEK, p38 MAPK, and FGFR/VEGFR were assessed after blockage. Cell phenotype was determined by flow cytometry and immunofluorescence. Colony-forming-unit and cell proliferation assays were performed. qRT-PCR for Alkaline Phosphatase (ALP), &amp;#946;-galactosidase, Collagen I (COL1), Osteocalcin (OC), Osteoprotegerin (OPG), Osterix, PAR1, Periostin (POSTN), RANKL and RUNX2 was conducted. ELISA was performed to COL1, OC, OPG, PAR1, POSTN and RANKL. Calcium deposition was quantified through ALP and Alizarin Red Staining. Cell sheet microstructure was analyzed through H&amp;E, light and scanning electron microscopy. In vivo, 14-day pre-induced hPDLSC sheets from the 3 groups were transplanted to Balb/c nude mice and evaluated after 60 days. Immunohistochemistry for bone sialoprotein (BSP), integrin &amp;#946;1, COL1 and histological stains (H&amp;E, Van Giesson, Masson's Trichrome and Von Kossa) was carried out. Ectopic bone formation was evaluated through micro-CT. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test (P value of 0.05) was used. PAR&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; activation significantly increased pro-osteogenic gene and protein expression, calcium deposition and enhanced ectopic bone formation in vivo.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>PAR&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; plays a major role in enhancing bone formation &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPESP N° 17/23158-0 | FAPESP N° 18/13818-5)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA018</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Association between poor oral health and adverse COVID-19 outcomes in hospitalized patients</Titulo>
		<Autores>Costa CA*, Vilela ACS, Oliveira SA, Leles CR, Costa NL</Autores>
		<Universidade>Periodontia - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE GOIÁS.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study aimed to assess the dental and periodontal status of hospitalized COVID-19 patients and their association with the incidence of adverse COVID-19 outcomes. 128 hospitalized patients with COVID-19 diagnosis were included. DMFT index, periodontal status, and tooth loss patterns (Eichner index) were assessed by means of in-hospital clinical examination. Associations between oral health measures, the severity of COVID-19 symptoms, and hospitalization endpoints were tested using chi-square test and prevalence ratio (PR) estimation using Generalized Linear Model (GLM) with log-Poisson regression with robust error variances. Oral health-related variables, comorbidities, and patient's age were included in the regression models using a block-wise selection of predictors. Poor oral health conditions were highly prevalent and associated with critical COVID-19 symptoms, higher risk for admission in the intensive care unit, and mortality. Periodontitis was significantly associated with ICU admission (PR=1.44; p=0.017), critical symptoms (PR=2.56; p=0.002), and risk of death (PR=2.02; p=0.028) when adjusted for age and comorbidities. Eichner index (B and C) was associated with ICU admission, probably affected by the relationship between advanced age and tooth loss.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The positive association between deleterious oral health-related conditions, especially periodontitis, and serious COVID-19 outcomes suggest that dental and periodontal status may play a role in the prognosis of hospitalized COVID-19 patients.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPEG N° #CVD2020051000009)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA019</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Tailoring Cu-loaded electrospun membrane with antibacterial ability for guided bone regeneration</Titulo>
		<Autores>Cordeiro JM*, Avila ED, Yang F, Beucken JD, Barão VAR</Autores>
		<Universidade>Prótese e Periodontia - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>We tailored copper (Cu)-loaded electrospun membranes for guided bone regeneration (GBR) targeting the stimulation of innate cells active in bone growth and the prevention of treatment-related infections. Functional GBR membranes were produced via an electrospinning set-up using a silk-based solution in association with polyethylene oxide (Silk:PEO - control). Experimental groups were loaded with Cu oxide (CuO 1%, CuO 0.5%, CuO 0.1%, and CuO 0.05%). The morphological, structural, chemical and mechanical properties of membranes were evaluated. Direct and indirect &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; cytocompatibility experiments were performed with human bone mesenchymal stem cells and human umbilical vein endothelial cells. The antibacterial potential of membranes was tested with &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; biofilm (24 h). One-way ANOVA and Tukey's HSD test were used for multiple comparisons (p&lt;0.05). CuO was successfully incorporated into membranes as clusters without affecting its mechanical resistance. Cu ions were released from the nanofibers over 1 week, being expressively greater in an acidic condition. Increased Cu concentration produced membranes with thinner nanofiber, greater porosity, and stronger antimicrobial effect (p&lt;0.01). CuO 0.1% and CuO 0.05% were able to support and stimulate cells adhesion and proliferation (p&lt;0.05), as well as angiogenesis.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The tailored functional Cu-loaded GBR membrane with combined cell stimulatory behavior and antibacterial capacity may be a valuable strategy to diminish the risk of infections and improve the regeneration process.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - Fapesp N° 2018/14117-0 | CNPq N° 304853/2018-6 | CAPES N° Finance Code 001)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA020</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Titanium with nanotopography inhibits osteoclast-induced disruption of osteoblast differentiation by regulating histone methylation</Titulo>
		<Autores>Bighetti-Trevisan RL*, Almeida LO, Gordon J, Tye C, Lian JB, Stein GS, Rosa AL, Beloti MM</Autores>
		<Universidade>Biologia Básica e Oral - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of this study was to evaluate the regulation of the osteoclast/osteoblast crosstalk by titanium with nanotopography (Ti Nano) and the mechanism involved in this process. Osteoblasts were cultured on Ti Nano and Ti Machined and osteoclasts into inserts in a co-culture model for 48 h, and non-cocultured osteoblasts were used as control. The RNAseq (DESeq2: FC&gt;1.7; p&amp;#8804;0.05) detected that osteoclasts downregulated the expression of genes related to osteogenesis and upregulated genes related to histone modification and chromatin organization in osteoblasts grown on both surfaces. Osteoclasts also inhibited (p&amp;#8804;0.05) the gene expression of &lt;em&gt;Runx2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dlx5&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alpl&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ibsp&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bglap&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Opg&lt;/em&gt; and protein expression of RUNX2 and ALPL, and such effect was reduced by Ti Nano. Regarding the mechanism, an increase in H3K9me2, H3K27me3 and EZH2 protein expression was observed on both Ti surfaces under coculture conditions (p&amp;#8804;0.05). ChIP assay revealed accumulation of H3K9me2 repressing the promoter region of &lt;em&gt;Alpl&lt;/em&gt; and H3K27me3 repressing &lt;em&gt;Runx2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alpl&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ibsp&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Opg&lt;/em&gt; in osteoblasts in the presence of osteoclasts, which were attenuated by Ti Nano. Immunofluorescence corroborated the ChIP assay, exhibiting less RUNX2 and ALPL and more H3K27me3 staining in osteoblasts under coculture conditions in a less pronounced way on Ti Nano.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In conclusion, Ti Nano may favor the clinical outcomes of implant osseointegration, since this nanotopography inhibited the osteoclast-induced disruption of osteoblast differentiation by reducing the accumulation of H3K9 and H3K27 methylated histones.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPESP  N° 2017/23888-8 | FAPESP N° 2018/17356-6 | CNPq N° 303464/2016-0)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
</Resumos>
